Bancroft Library. Regional Oral History Office Oral History Interviews
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Bancroft Library. Regional Oral History Office Oral History Interviews 1959-1979 1969-1975
MSS54221
Bancroft Library. Regional Oral History Office
19 items
8 containers
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Interviews pertaining to California state politics and government, the suffragists, and to the life and career of John S. Service, an American diplomat in China, and his wife, Caroline Service.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bary, Helen Valeska, 1887-1973. Helen Valeska Bary oral history interview.; Field, Sara Bard, 1882-1974. Sara Bard Field oral history interview.; Gordon, Walter, 1894-1976. Walter Gordon oral history interview.; Kent, Roger, 1906-1980. Roger Kent oral history interview.; Matthews, Burnita Shelton, 1894-1988. Burnita Shelton Matthews oral history interview.; Paul, Alice, 1885-1977. Alice Paul oral history interview.; Rankin, Jeannette, 1880-1973. Jeannette Rankin oral history interview.; Reyher, Rebecca Hourwich, 1897-1987. Rebecca Hourwich Reyher oral history interview.; Service, Caroline. Caroline Service oral history interview.; Service, John S. (John Stewart), 1909-1999.; Vernon, Mabel. Mabel Vernon oral history interview.; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974.
Organizations
Bancroft Library. Regional Oral History Office.; Earl Warren Oral History Project (Bancroft Library); Governmental History Documentation Project (Bancroft Library); John S. and Caroline Service Oral History Project (Bancroft Library); Suffragists Oral History Project.; Walter Gordon Oral History Project (Bancroft Library)
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--China.; Diplomats' spouses--Interviews.; Labor unions--California.; Politicians--California--Interviews.; Suffragists--Interviews.; Women--Suffrage.
Places
California--Politics and government--1850-1950.; California--Politics and government--1951-; China--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--China.
Acquisition Information
The Oral History Collection of the Bancroft Library Regional Oral History Office, University of California at Berkeley, was given to the Library of Congress by the Bancroft Library from 1974 to 1987 and by Amelia Fry in 1985.
Microfiche
The Earl Warren Oral History Project and the Suffragist Oral History Project are also available on microfiche in the Library of Congress Microform Reading Room.
Scope and Content Note
The Oral History Collection spans the years 1959 to 1979 and consists of nineteen volumes containing transcripts of approximately eighty interviews conducted by the Bancroft Library Regional Oral History Office at the University of California at Berkeley. The transcripts are accompanied by introductions, tables of content, indexes, and supplementary material including photographs and copies of correspondence, reports, and clippings. The interviews are arranged alphabetically by name of the oral history project.
The bulk of the interviews relate to California state government and politics. They include twenty-seven interviews from the Earl Warren Oral History Project concerning health insurance, labor, forced removal and incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II, Warren's early years in Bakersfield, and his relations as governor with the public, press, and state legislature. An extensive interview with Merrell Farnham Small, administrative secretary in the governor's office from 1945 to 1953, is also included. Other oral history projects pertaining to California are the Governmental History Documentation Project which is represented in this collection by an interview with Roger Kent, vice chairman and chairman of the California Democratic State Central Committee from 1954 to 1965, and an oral history project documenting the career of Walter Gordon, lawyer, civil rights leader, governor of the Virgin Islands, and chairman of the California Adult Authority, a state agency responsible for setting terms and granting paroles for adult prison inmates.
The collection also contains thirteen interviews from the Suffragists Oral History Project. Included are interviews with Helen Valeska Bary, Sara Bard Field, Burnita Shelton Matthews, Alice Paul, Jeannette Rankin, Rebecca Hourwich Reyher, and Mabel Vernon, among others. The interviews explore their subject's early formative years and their subsequent efforts on behalf of woman's suffrage, welfare and labor reform, world peace, and passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. An interview with Caroline Service, wife of diplomat John S. Service, forms part of the China Series. Her interview covers her years in China from 1933 to 1940 as the wife of a foreign service officer and her husband's arrest in 1945 for allegedly passing secret documents to Amerasia magazine, his testimony before the Loyalty Review Board in 1951, and his subsequent firing by the State Department.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by name of oral history project.
Container List
- China Series, John S. and Caroline Service Oral History Project, interviews with Caroline Service, 1976 (Box 1)
- Earl Warren Oral History Project (Box 1)
  - "Earl Warren and Health Insurance, 1943-49," interviews with Gordon Claycombe, John W. Cline, Russel V. Lee, and Byrl R. Salsman, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - "Earl Warren's Bakersfield," interviews with Maryann Ashe, Omar Cavins, Ruth Smith Henley, Ralph Kreiser, Manford Martin, and Ernest McMillan, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - "The Governor and the Public, the Press, and the Legislature," interviews with Marguerite Gallagher, Verne Scoggins, and Beach Vasey, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - "Japanese-American Relocation Reviewed" (Box 2)
    - Vol. 1, "Decision and Exodus," interviews with Tom Clark, Edward Ennis, Percy C. Heckendorf, James Rowe, and Herbert Wenig, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 2, "The Internment," interviews with Robert Cozzens, Ruth Kingman, and Dillon S. Myer, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - "Labor Looks at Earl Warren," interviews with Germain Bulcke, Joseph W. Chaudet, Paul Heide, U. S. Simonds, and Ernest H. Vernon, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - "Merrell Farnham Small, Departmental Secretary," interviews with Small, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
- Governmental History Documentation Project, "Roger Kent: Building the Democratic Party in California, 1954-66," interviews with Kent, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
- Suffragists Oral History Project (Box 4)
  - Bary, Helen Valeska, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Butler, Jessie Haver, Miriam Allen deFord, Ernestine Hara Kettler, Laura Ellsworth Seiler, and Sylvie Grace Thompson Thygeson, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Field, Sara Bard, 1959-1963 (Box 5)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Paul, Alice, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Rankin, Jeannette, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Reyher, Rebecca Hourwich, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Vernon, Mabel, and Hazel Hunkins-Hallinan, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
  - Walter Gordon Oral History Project, interviews with Gordon, his associates, and family, 1971-1979, (2 vols.) (Box 8)